How much blood would you shed to stay alive?
Saw is a horror, mystery, crime film directed by James Wan.
Two men wake up to find themselves shackled in a grimy, abandoned bathroom.
As they struggle to comprehend their predicament, they discover a disturbing
tape left behind by the sadistic mastermind known as Jigsaw.
With a chilling voice and cryptic instructions, Jigsaw informs them that they
must partake in a gruesome game in order to secure their freedom.
John Kramer / Jigsaw, played by Tobin Bell.
Dr. Lawrence Gordon, played by Cary Elwes.
Adam Faulkner-Stanheight, played by Leigh Whannell.
David Tapp, played by Danny Glover.
Alison Gordon, played by Monica Potter.
Detective Steven Sing, played by Ken Leung.
Saw is a 2004 American psychological horror thriller film directed by James Wan in his feature
directorial debut, and written by Leigh Whannell, from a story by Wan and Whannell.
It stars Whannell alongside Cary Elwes, Danny Glover,
Monica Potter, Michael Emerson, and Ken Leung.
The film tells a nonlinear narrative revolving around the mystery of the Jigsaw Killer, who tests his victims' will to live by
putting them through deadly "games" where they must inflict great physical pain upon themselves to survive.
The frame story follows Jigsaw's latest victims (Whannell and Elwes), who awaken in a large,
dilapidated bathroom, with one being ordered to kill the other to save his own family.
The screenplay was written by Whannell, who co-created the story
with Wan in their respective screenwriting debuts.
The film was originally written in 2001, but after failed attempts to get the script produced in Wan
and Whannell's home country of Australia, they were urged to travel to Los Angeles.
In order to help attract producers, they shot a low-budget short
film of the same name from a scene out of the script.
This proved successful in 2003 as producers were immediately attached and
also formed a horror genre production label, Twisted Pictures.
The film was given a small production budget and was shot in 18 days.
Saw was first screened at the 2004 Sundance Film Festival on January 19, 2004.
Due to positive audience reception, Lions Gate picked up
the distribution rights for the film.
Originally planned for a straight-to-video release, they decided to instead
release the film in theaters in North America on October 29, 2004.
The film received mixed reviews from critics.
After topping the opening weekend box office, the film would go on to gross $104 million
worldwide to become one of the most profitable horror films since Scream (1996).
The success of Saw launched a media franchise, including several
sequels, video games, theme park rides, and merchandising.
The first sequel, titled Saw II, was released the
following year in October 2005.
The film explores themes of sadism, shotgun, detective, flashback, hospital.
The tone is dark and mind_bending.